Guide to the Peace and Freedom Center of Pittsburgh Records, 1967-1969 AIS.1969.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Peace and Freedom Center of Pittsburgh Records
1967-1969
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Peace and Freedom Center (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1969.06
2.5 Linear Feet
The Peace and Freedom Center was a Pittsburgh based anti-war group in the 1960s and 1970s. It was originally located in the East Liberty neighborhood of Pittsburgh, until its offices moved to the Bloomfield neighborhood. The collection contains meeting minutes, correspondence, posters, results from opinion polls and information concerning different events associated with the group.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Walter Tillow on April 24, 1969.
Previous Citation
Peace and Freedom Center of Pittsburgh Records, 1967-1969, AIS.1969.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
History
The Peace and Freedom Center of Pittsburgh was an educational and social action organization dedicated to the elimination of war, poverty, exploitation and the inhumanity of man. It promoted the active participation of people through the formation of a movement to build a society in which people have meaningful control over the political, social and economic institutions, which shape their lives.
The center was originally located in the East Liberty neighborhood of Pittsburgh, 1968-1969. It moved to the Bloomfield section of Pittsburgh in 1969. As of the last records, 1970, that is where the Center remained.
The Center took an active roll in the community, hosting events, taking opinion polls and participating in rallies and protests. The Center was aligned with similar groups around the nation. The Peace and Freedom Center also published a newsletter four times a year from 1966 through 1970.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection reflects the activities of the Peace and Freedom Center of Pittsburgh as well as the activities of other groups who were associated with their cause. The collection consists of six boxes containing meeting minutes, posters, polling information, newsletters and correspondence with other groups in the United States, as well as information on events in which the Center participated.
The collection has been divided into the following series. Series I contains administrative records, personnel files, news releases, correspondence as well as publications from the Peace and Freedom Center. Series II holds opinion polls produced by the center. Series III has information on meetings and conferences. Series IV has information on various organizations connected with the Peace and Freedom Center. Series V contains information, in the form of speeches, publications and correspondence, generated by various people. Series VI contains information on draft and anti-draft movements, the Vietnam War, human rights and poverty. Series VII contains newsletters published by various organizations that were in accordance with issues that the Peace and Freedom Center valued.
Newsletters; Correspondence; Activists; Social advocacy -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies, etc.; Posters; Minutes (Administrative records); Public opinion polls; Economic assistance, Domestic -- United States -- Societies, etc.; Human rights workers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Human rights advocacy -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies, etc.; Peace movements -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies, etc.; Social action; Associations; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Peace and Freedom Center (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Administration Records, Publications, and Personnel, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains administrative records, lease information, news releases, publications produced by the organization, and information about the field secretary and office manager.
  - Organization, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lease and lease notices, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - News releases, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pittsburgh Peace and Freedom News Vol. 1 #1 - Vol. 4 #2, July 1966 - March 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Field secretary Tillow, Walter. Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Office manager Jones, Ruth M. Correspondence and memoranda, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Opinion Polls, II.
  This series includes information collected as the result of opinion polls from 1967.
  - Vietnam War, East Liberty, individual interviews, Summer 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Assignment sheets, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Vietnam War, poll information, Summer 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Vietnam War, Garfield, individual interviews, Summer 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Vietnam War, Hazelwood, individual interviews, Summer 1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hazelwood, data by street, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hazelwood, data by street, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Vietnam War, Hazelwood, summary of poll, Summer 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Meetings, Conferences, III.
  The information in this series deals with meetings and conferences the Center either had interest in or was a participant.
  - Crisis of Conscience Conference, Pittsburgh, Pa., October 11-13, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Democratic Party National Convention, Coalition protest at Chicago convention, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Operation Freedom Board minutes, September 9, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Workshop - independent political groups, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Resolutions, memorials in regards to Vietnam War, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Organizations, IV.
  This series contains information on organizations which were either involved with or were of interest to the Peace and Freedom Center. The files are arranged alphabetically.
  - Americans for Democratic Action, Pittsburgh, Pa. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Chicago Area Draft Resisters (Cadre) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clergy and Laymen Concerned About Vietnam (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committee for the Presidio 27 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Committee to Free Morton Sobell (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Communist Party U.S.A. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Detroit Women for Peace (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dow Action Committee (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Episcopal Peace Fellowship, Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fort Hood Three Defense Committee (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Independent Student Unions, Erie Chapter (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - International Union of Students (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Labor Leadership Assembly for Peace (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lawyers Committee on American policy towards Vietnam (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Montreal Council to aid War Resisters (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Committee to Abolish the House Committee on un-American Activities (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Conference for New Politics (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National Mobilization committee to End the War in Vietnam (CEWV) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Negotiation Now! Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - New Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam (CEWV) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - New University Conference, Chicago (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - New University Conference, Pittsburgh (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Philadelphia Resistance (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Pittsburgh Ad Hoc committee on Vietnam (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Pittsburgh Area Students for Peace (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pittsburgh Black Draft Counseling Center (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Pittsburgh Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Pittsburgh Committee on Southern Africa (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Pittsburgh Committee to End the War in Vietnam (EWV) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Pittsburgh Resistance (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Pittsburgh Veterans for Peace, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Resist, Cambridge, Massachusetts, correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - The Resistance, N.Y., correspondence, from April 1968 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLS), April 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Southern Conference Educational Fund (SCEF) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Spring Mobilization Committee, Pittsburgh, Pa. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Student Mobilization Committee, New York, N.Y. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - SDS, University of Pittsburgh (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Tieng Noi Cua Phat Tu Viet Nam Hai Ngoai - Voice of the Vietnam Buddhists Students for Peace, University of Pittsburgh (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Union of Vietnamese Students in France, April 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - United Farm Workers, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - United Oakland Ministry, Pittsburgh, Pa. (posters) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Vietnam Moratorium Committee (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Vietnam Summer (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Vietnam Summer (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - W.E.B. DuBoi Clubs, N.Y. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - W.E.B. DuBois Clubs, Pittsburgh (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Western Pennsylvania Academic Council on Problems of War and Peace (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Women Strike for Peace, Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Youth International Movements (YIPPIE) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Mailing List of Organizations Opposing the War in Vietnam (Box 3, Folder 21)
- People, V.
  The files in this series contain information, in the form of speeches, publications and correspondence, generated by the people listed below.
  - Atlee, John (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Brown, H. Raps (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gregory, Dick (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newton, Henry P. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Peck, Sidney (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Rodd, Thomas (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Spock, Dr. Benjamin, October 22, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Literature, Sources and Posters, VI.
  In this series there is information on draft and anti-draft movements, the Vietnam War, human rights and poverty.
  - Literature. Draft/Anti-Draft, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Literature. Vietnam War, negro (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Literature. Vietnam War, religious groups (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Literature. Vietnam War, detailed "Hawk" (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Literature. Brochures and Literature on the Draft and Vietnam War (Pittsburgh groups) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Literature. Vietnam War, general (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Literature. Resistance (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Literature. Resistance (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Literature. Resistance support (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Literature. Human rights, poverty, free university, politics, etc. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Sources for material (anti-war/anti-draft) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Posters (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Publications, VII.
  This series contains newsletters published by various organizations that were in accordance with issues that the Peace and Freedom Center valued.
  - Miscellaneous publications Vietnam ROTC, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - AIM the Bulletin of the American Independence Movement (published by IPAC), August-December 1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - American Exile in Britain, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - American Exile in Canada, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Amnesty Action, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Another Mother for Peace, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Chicago Action Community, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - CIPA newsletter (Citizens for Independent Action), undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Catholic Radical, February 1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Conscience Guide Newsletter, April 1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Detroit Women for Peace, January 1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - The Free You, Free University, April 1969 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Freedom and Peace Free Press, March 1969 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Houston Committee to End the War in Vietnam News (HCEWV), March 1968 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Insurgent W.E.B DuBois Clubs of America, Summer 1968 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Iowa Peace Bulletin, February-July 1968 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Labor News and Views, December 1967 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Left Out News (Citizens for Independent Political Action), July 1967-August 1967 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Libert (Citizens Committee for Constitutional Liberties), June 1963-Fall 1968 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Long Island United for Peace Reporter, August 1967 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - MDS Newsletter (New Orleans Movement for a Democratic Society), December 1967-January 1968 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Massachusetts PAX News (Political Action for Peace), October -December 1967 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Milwaukee 14 Newsletter, January-March 1969 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Milwaukee Organizer, July 1967, October 1967 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Minnesota Vietnam News, September 1967, October 1967 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - The Minority of One, January 1966-September 1967 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Mississippi Newsletter, October 1967-November 1968 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Mobilizer to End the War in Vietnam, September 1967, August 1968 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - The Movement, San Francisco, February 1968-February 1969 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - National Convention for New Politics News, September 1967, August 1968 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - National Mobilization Direct Action Project Direct Action News, September 1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Negotiation Now: Bulletin, August 1967 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The New England Free Press, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - New Mobilizer, September 5, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - New Patriot (Ithaca, N.Y.), December 1967-July 1968 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Ohio Peace Action News, January 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Paper Tiger, Boston, Mass., undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Paris Digest, April 1968 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The Partisan, Fall 1967 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - PAX Chicago Peace Council News Bulleting, December 1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Peace Center Newsletter, Harrisburg Area Peace Center, October 1967-June 1968 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Pennsylvania Activist, February 1966, June 1968 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - People for Human Rights Newsletter, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Philadelphia Anti-Draft Union Newsletter, January 1968 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Radicals in the Professions, November 1967-May 1968 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Raritan Peace News, October 1967-February 1968 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Resist!, December 1967, April 1969 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - The Resister, February 22, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Reveille, June 1968 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Rochester Peace Newsletter, September 1967-October 1968 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - SCEF News (Southern Conference Education Fund), June 1968 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - SDRU Newsletter (Swarthmore Draft Resistance Union), August 1967 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - SSRS Newsletter (Society for Social Responsibility in Science), October -November 1967 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - South Vietnam In Struggle, March 1, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - The Southern Patriot, August 1967-March 1969 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Spur Newsletter W.E.B. DuBois Clubs of America, inventory sheet, November 1967 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Student Mobilizer, July 1967-January 1968 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Student Mobilization committee (SMC), National Action Bulletin, October 1968 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Socialist Worker Campaigner, January 1968 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Talk Out. (Mantua-Powelton Vietnam Project), June 1967 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Tri-Continental Information Center Bulletin, November 1967-January 1968 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - UT Peaceletter (University of Texas Committee to End the War in Vietnam), undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Vietnam Commencement Newsletter, March 1968 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Vietnam Petitioner (Newsletter of the Boston, Cambridge, Harvard, Radcliff and MIT Committees to End the War in Vietnam), April 1967 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Vietnam Summer, Indianapolis Project News, July 1967 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Vietnam Summer News, June-August 1967 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Vietnam War, What For?, January-February 1968 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Vocations for Social Change, March, April 1969 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Voice of the Women's Liberation Movement, February 1969 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - We Won't Go (Newsletter of the Philadelphia Anti-Draft Union), November 1967 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Women Strike for Peace, memo, August 1967-February 1969 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Women Strike for Peace, newsletter, June 1968 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Wyoming Valley Committee of Concern for Vietnam, April 1969 (Box 6, Folder 44)